Margarita Froman Papers
© 2004 University of Connecticut
Margarita Froman Papers.
undated, 1916-1971.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Froman [Frohman], Margarita.
.5 linear feet.
Margarita Frohman was born in Moscow, Russia, in October 1896. At the age of eight, she was one of ten selected to study ballet at the Imperial School of Ballet in Moscow. She graduated in her early teens and was engaged immediately as a soloist in the Moscow Bolshoi Theatre. After many years in Yugoslavia (1917-1957), Froman emmigrated to the United States in 1957 settling in New London, CT.
MSS19710001
Biography
Margarita Frohman was born in Moscow, Russia, in October 1896. At the age of eight, she was one of ten selected to study ballet at the Imperial School of Ballet in Moscow. She graduated in her early teens and was engaged immediately as a soloist in the Moscow Bolshoi Theatre. She toured the cultural centers of europe with the Diaghileff group, which also included Pavlova, Nijinsky, Karsavina, Fokine, Fokina in its membership. After many years in Yugoslavia (1917-1957) as Maitresse de Ballet of the Yugoslavian Croatian National Theatre and producer and choreographer for ballet and opera at the Yugoslav National Ballet, Froman emmigrated to the United States in 1957 settling in New London, CT. She taught at the Froman Professional School of Ballet (New London), the Connecticut School of Music (Willimantic), the Hartford Conservatory and the University of Connecticut. Margarita Froman died in 1970.
Scope and Content
Collection includes photographs, ballet programs and newspaper clippings describing her career.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Ballerinas--Russia--Biography.; Ballerinas--Yugoslavia--Biography.; Dance teachers--Connecticut.
Document Types:
Publications.; Photographs.
Occupations:
Ballerina.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the University of Connecticut by Olga Froman in the Spring of 1971.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1916-1971
  - "Les Sylphides" (New York), 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 1-3)
  - "Spectre de la Rose" (New York), 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Ballet Russe in New York, 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Ballet Russe Program, United States Tour (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Court Square Theatre, Springfield, MA, 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Margarita Froman and Ninette de Valois, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Yugoslav National Opera and Ballet, London Tour, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 10-11)
  - Prince Igor (London), 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Stoll Theatre, London, England, 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Festival Internazionale del Balleto (Genoa), 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - "Manon Lescaut" (Zagreb), 1941 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - "Rapsodija" (Kiev), 1917 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Nutcracker-Schiaccianoci (Milan), 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 20-24)
  - "La Gioconda" (Milan), 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - "Sadko" (Milan), 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
  - Margarita Froman, Tamara Karsavina and unidentified teacher(Belgrad), ca. 1930 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - "La Honza" (Belgrad), 1930 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - "Musical Pony" (Belgrad), undated (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - "Queen of Spades" (Zagreb), ca. 1935 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - "The Gingerbread Heart" (Zagreb), 1935 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - "Sadko", undated (Box 1:, Folder 36-40)
  - "Le Tricorne" (Belgrad), 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - "Sadko", undated (Box 1:, Folder 42-44)
  - "The Gingerbread Heart" (Zagreb), 1935 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
  - Belgrad Opera Season, 1963-1964 (Box 1:, Folder 48)
  - Maragrita Froman (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 49)
  - "Faust" (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 50)
  - Russian Dance (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 52)
  - "Gavotte" (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
  - "Carnival" (Belgrad), ca. 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 55)
  - Margarita Froman (Zagreb), 1923 (Box 1:, Folder 56-58)
  - Margarita Froman (Zagreb), 1940s (Box 1:, Folder 60)
  - Margarita Froman, ca. 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 62)
  - Margarita Froman at the Folies-Bergère (Paris), 1936 (Box 1:, Folder 64)
  - "Columbine" (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 66)
  - Norwegian Dance (Zagreb), ca. 1925 (Box 1:, Folder 67)
  - "Visions Nocturnes" (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 68)
  - "Tamara" (Zagreb), ca. 1924 (Box 1:, Folder 69)
  - "Boyar's Dance" (Zagreb), 1921 (Box 1:, Folder 70)
  - Spanish Dance, undated (Box 1:, Folder 71)
  - "Faust", ca. 1927 (Box 1:, Folder 72)
  - "Firebird" (Zagreb), ca. 1931-1932 (Box 1:, Folder 74)
  - "Aziade" (Moscow), 1917 (Box 1:, Folder 77-78)
  - Swiss Dance (Kiev), 1917 (Box 1:, Folder 79)
  - "Raimonda" (Belgrad), ca. 1929 (Box 1:, Folder 80)
  - New York Times articles, 1916 (Box 1:, Folder 81)
  - Reviews of La Scala Productions, 1938 (Box 1:, Folder 82)
  - "Prince Igor" (Zagreb), 1954 (Box 1:, Folder 83)
  - "Romeo I Julija" (Zagreb), 1948 (Box 1:, Folder 84)
  - Hartford Conservatory, 1959 (Box 1:, Folder 85)
  - "Spring Fairy", 1963 (Box 1:, Folder 86)
  - Skibine, George, 1965 (Box 1:, Folder 87)
  - Notice for Froman's 70th Birthday, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 88)
  - Biographical information, undated (Box 1:, Folder 89)
  - Novoye Russkoye Slovo, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 90)
  - Obituaries, 1970-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 91)
  - Unidentified materials, undated (Box 1:, Folder 92-95)